Are we the only living things in the entire universe?
我们是整个宇宙中唯一的生命吗？
The observable universe is about 90 billion light-years in diameter.
可观测宇宙的直径约为900亿光年。
There are at least 100 billion galaxies, each with 100 to 1000 billion stars.
至少有1000亿个星系，每个星系有1000亿到1万亿颗恒星。
Recently, we've learned that planets are very common too, and there are probably trillions
最近我们发现行星也非常普遍，宇宙中可能存在数以万亿计的
and trillions of habitable planets in the universe, which means there should be lots
适宜居住的星球，这意味着生命应该有很多机会
of opportunity for life to develop and exist, right?
诞生和存在，对吧？
But where is it?
但它们在哪里？
Shouldn't the universe be teeming with spaceships?
宇宙里不应该到处都是飞船吗？
Let's take a step back.
让我们退一步思考。
Even if there are alien civilizations in other galaxies, there's no way we'll ever know
即使其他星系中存在外星文明，我们也永远无法
about them.
了解到它们。
Basically, everything outside of our direct galactic neighborhood, the so-called local group, is
基本上，我们所在的本星系群以外的一切，
pretty much out of our reach forever because of the expansion of the universe.
由于宇宙膨胀，将永远超出我们的触及范围。
Even if we had really fast spaceships, it would literally take billions of years to reach
即使我们拥有极快的飞船，到达那些地方
these places, traveling through the emptiest areas in the universe.
也需要数十亿年，穿越宇宙中最空旷的区域。
So let's focus on the Milky Way.
所以让我们聚焦在银河系。
The Milky Way is our home galaxy.
银河系是我们的家园星系。
It consists of up to 400 billion stars.
它拥有多达4000亿颗恒星。
That's a lot of stars.
那是非常多的恒星。
Counting one per second, it would take you 100 lifetimes to count them all.
如果每秒数一颗，你需要100辈子才能数完。
There are about 20 billion sun-like stars in the Milky Way, and estimates suggest that
银河系中约有200亿颗类太阳恒星，估计其中
a fifth of them have an Earth-sized planet in its habitable zone, the area with conditions
五分之一在宜居带内拥有地球大小的行星——
that enable life to exist.
那是能够存在生命的区域。
If only 0.1% of those planets harbored life, there would be one million planets with life
如果仅有0.1%的行星存在生命，银河系中就会有
in the Milky Way.
一百万个有生命的星球。
But wait, there's more.
但等等，还有更多。
The Milky Way is about 13 billion years old.
银河系大约有130亿年的历史。
In the beginning, it would not have been a good place for life, because things exploded
起初，它并不适合生命存在，因为
a lot.
爆炸非常频繁。
But after 1 to 2 billion years, the first habitable planets were born.
但在10至20亿年后，第一批宜居行星诞生了。
Earth is only 4 billion years old, so there have probably been trillions of chances for
地球只有40亿年历史，因此在过去，其他星球上
life to develop on other planets in the past.
可能已经有过数万亿次生命诞生的机会。
If only a single one of them had developed into a space-traveling supercivilization, we
如果其中哪怕只有一个发展成了能星际旅行的超级文明，
would have noticed by now.
我们早就应该注意到了。
What would such a civilization look like?
这样的文明会是什么样子？
There are three categories.
共有三个等级。
A Type I civilization would be able to access the whole energy available on its planet.
I型文明能够利用其星球上所有可用的能量。
In case you're wondering, we're currently around 0.73 on the scale, and we should reach
如果你好奇的话，我们目前在这个量表上大约是0.73，
Type I sometime in the next couple of hundred years.
预计在未来几百年内达到I型。
Type II would be a civilization capable of harnessing all of the energy of its home star.
II型文明能够利用其母星的全部能量。
This would require some serious science fiction, but it is doable in principle.
这需要极其超前的科技，但理论上是可行的。
Just like the Dyson Sphere, a giant complex surrounding the sun would be conceivable.
就像戴森球一样——围绕太阳的巨型结构是可以设想的。
Type III is a civilization that basically controls its whole galaxy and its energy.
III型文明基本上控制了整个星系及其能量。
An alien race this advanced would probably be godlike to us.
如此先进的外星种族对我们来说可能如同神明。
But why should we be able to see such an alien civilization in the first place?
但我们为什么首先能够看见这样的外星文明呢？
If we were to build generation spaceships that could sustain a population for around 1,000
如果我们建造能维持约1000年人口的代际飞船，
years, we could colonize the whole galaxy in 2 million years.
我们可以在200万年内殖民整个银河系。
Looks like a long time.
听起来是很长的时间。
But remember, the Milky Way is huge.
但请记住，银河系非常巨大。
So if it takes a couple of million years to colonize the entire galaxy, and there are possibly
所以，如果殖民整个银河系需要几百万年，而银河系中
millions if not billions of planets that sustain life in the Milky Way, and these other life
可能有数百万甚至数十亿个有生命的星球，
forms have had considerably more time than we've had, then where are all the aliens?
而这些生命形式拥有的时间比我们多得多，那么外星人在哪里？
This is the Fermi Paradox, and nobody has an answer to it.
这就是费米悖论，没有人知道答案。
But we do have some ideas.
但我们有一些想法。
Let's talk about filters.
让我们来谈谈"过滤器"。
A filter in this context represents a barrier that is really hard for life to overcome.
在这个语境中，过滤器代表生命难以跨越的障碍。
They come in various degrees of scary.
它们有各种不同的可怕程度。
There are great filters and we have passed them.
第一种：有巨大过滤器，而我们已经通过了。
Maybe it is way harder for complex life to develop than we think.
也许复杂生命的演化比我们想象的要困难得多。
The process allowing life to begin hasn't yet been completely figured out, and the conditions
生命起源的过程至今尚未完全弄清楚，
required may be really complicated.
所需条件可能极其复杂。
Maybe in the past, the universe was way more hostile, and only recently have things cooled
也许过去宇宙环境更加恶劣，只是最近才
down to make complex life possible.
冷却到允许复杂生命存在的程度。
This would also mean that we may be unique, or at least one of the first, if not the first
这也意味着我们可能是独一无二的，或者至少是
civilization in the entire universe.
整个宇宙中最早的文明之一。
Two, there are great filters, and they are ahead of us.
第二种：有巨大过滤器，而它在我们前方。
This one would be really, really bad.
这种情况会非常非常糟糕。
Maybe life on our level exists everywhere in the universe, but it gets destroyed when
也许像我们这样的生命在宇宙中到处存在，
it reaches a certain point, a point that lies ahead of us.
但当它们达到某个阶段时就会被摧毁——那个阶段就在我们前面。
For example, awesome future technology exists, but when activated, it destroys the planet.
例如，未来的某种超级技术存在，但一旦启动就会毁灭星球。
The last words of every advanced civilization would be, this new device will solve all of
每个先进文明的遗言都会是："这个新装置将解决我们所有的问题，
our problems once I push this button.
只要我按下这个按钮。"
If this is true, then we are closer to the end than the beginning of human existence.
如果这是真的，那么我们离人类存在的终点比起点更近。
Or maybe there is an ancient type 3 civilization that monitors the universe, and once civilization
或者，也许存在一个古老的III型文明在监视宇宙，
is advanced enough, it gets eliminated in an instant.
一旦某个文明足够先进，就会被瞬间消灭。
Maybe there is something out there that it would be better not to discover.
也许有某些东西是最好不要发现的。
There is no way for us to know.
我们无法知晓。
One final thought, maybe we are alone.
最后一个想法：也许我们是孤独的。
Right now, we have no evidence that there is any life besides us.
目前，我们没有任何证据表明除我们之外还有其他生命。
Nothing.
什么都没有。
The universe appears to be empty and dead.
宇宙似乎是空旷而死寂的。
No one sending us messages, no one answering our calls.
没有人向我们发送信息，没有人回应我们的呼唤。
We may be completely alone, trapped on a tiny moist mud ball in an eternal universe.
我们可能完全孤独，困在永恒宇宙中一颗渺小潮湿的泥球上。
Does that thought scare you?
这个想法让你感到恐惧吗？
If it does, you are having the correct emotional reaction.
如果是的话，你的情绪反应是正确的。
If we let life on this planet die, perhaps there will be no life left in the universe.
如果我们让这颗星球上的生命消亡，也许宇宙中将再无生命。
Life will be gone, maybe forever.
生命将消逝，也许永远消逝。
If this is the case, we just have to venture to the stars and become the first type 3 civilization
如果真是这样，我们就必须踏上星际之旅，成为第一个III型文明，
to keep the delicate flame of life existing and to spread it until the universe breathes
守护生命这脆弱的火焰，将它传播，直到宇宙
its final breath and vanishes into oblivion.
呼出最后一口气，消逝于虚无。
The universe is too beautiful not to be experienced by someone.
宇宙太美了，不应该没有人来欣赏它。
This video was made possible by your support.
这个视频因你们的支持而得以制作。
It takes at least 200 hours to make one of our videos, and thanks to your contributions on Patreon,
制作我们的每一个视频至少需要200小时，感谢你们在Patreon上的贡献，
we are slowly able to do more and more of them.
我们得以慢慢制作更多视频。
If you want to help us out, and get your own personal bird for example, check out the Patreon page.
如果你想支持我们，并获得你自己专属的小鸟，请查看我们的Patreon页面。